Chester A. Smith Collection
Chester A. Smith Collection
1792-1970
Smith, Chester Allen, 1884-
26.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, Peekskill civic leader and Methodist Church activist. Collection contains personal and business papers, correspondence, manuscripts, diaries, family material, and clippings.
148671
Biographical History
Chester A. Smith (1884-1972) was a resident of Peekskill in Westchester County, New York. He was a politician, writer, court stenographer, the author of several books, and a delegate to the 1933 New York convention for ratification of the 21st Amendment (repeal of Prohibition). He was also an active lay member of the Methodist Church and attended at least twelve General Conferences, including the 1960 Conference in Denver which took up the question of whether or not to continue segregation within its administrative structure, in the form of the separate "Central Jurisdiction." Smith spoke up strongly against the policy.
For more information, see "Chester A. Smith and the Fight to Make Peekskill a City," available online at http://notorc.blogspot.com/2010/04/chester-smith-and-fight-to-make.html.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Chester A. Smith Collection has been arranged according to subject matter into 13 categories: clippings, correspondence, files, legal matters, Edwin Markham, Methodist Church, memorabilia, parental effects, photographs, miscellaneous printed material, writings, diaries, and bound records.
One item of interest in the Files is a letter signed by former President Woodrow Wilson. The Parental effects series contains sympathy cards received at Smith's sister's death and the diaries and papers of his father. Also of interest is a New Testament printed in New York by William Durell in 1792.
Arrangement of the Collection
Clippings, correspondence and diaries are arranged chronologically. All other material is arranged alphabetically by name, type of material, or topic.
Related Material
has a substantial number of collections relating to Methodist church and clergy, as well as many printed items cataloged in our Rare Book holdings. Please refer to for a complete listing of manuscript collections, and search for cataloged items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Smith, Chester Allen, 1884-; Methodists -- United States.; Peekskill (N.Y.); Correspondence.; Deeds.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1854 (Box 1)
  - 1883 (Box 1)
  - 1890-1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911-1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1960, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1961-1970, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Cards
    - Greeting, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Postal, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Pre-1900 (Box 2)
    - 1901-1920, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1921-1930, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1921-1930 (Box 3)
    - 1931-1940, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1941-1950, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1951-1960, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - 1961-1967, 10 folders (Box 4)
  - Telegrams (Box 4)
- Files
  - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - A (Box 5)
  - Affidavits (Box 5)
  - American Committee for Nonparticipation in Japanese Aggression (Box 5)
  - Autographs, Woodrow Wilson (Box 5)
  - B (Box 5)
  - Beautifying City (Box 5)
  - Bible (Box 5)
  - Bohlmann-Stevens Park (Box 5)
  - Books (Box 5)
  - Brown Plaza (Box 5)
  - Burke (Box 5)
  - C, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Cartoons (Box 5)
  - Checks (Box 5)
  - Church (Box 5)
  - Clinton (Box 5)
  - Committee
    - History (Box 5)
    - Non-Partisan, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Welfare (Box 5)
  - Cooper Park (Box 5)
  - Croton Valley (Box 5)
  - Curtis (Box 5)
  - D (Box 5)
  - Death Curve (Box 5)
  - Depew (Box 5)
  - Drew Seminary (Box 5)
  - E (Box 6)
  - Edith (Box 6)
  - Expenses (Box 6)
  - Experiences (Box 6)
  - F (Box 6)
  - First Methodist Church (Box 6)
  - Friendly Town Park (Box 6)
  - G, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - God's Reserves (Box 6)
  - I (Box 6)
  - J, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - K (Box 6)
  - L (Box 6)
  - League of Nations (Box 6)
  - Letters, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Library (Box 6)
  - Lincoln (Box 6)
  - M (Box 7)
  - MacKellar (Box 7)
  - Markham Association (Box 7)
  - Morschauser (Box 7)
  - Museum, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - N (Box 7)
  - National Assets (Box 7)
  - Carl Nelson (Box 7)
  - Non-Conformists (Box 7)
  - Non-Partisans (Box 7)
  - North Alcove (Box 7)
  - O (Box 7)
  - P (Box 7)
  - Parks (Box 7)
  - Peekskill (Box 7)
  - Peterson, Caleb (Box 7)
  - Program Committee (Box 7)
  - R (Box 7)
  - S, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Scholarship
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Committee (Box 7)
    - Fund, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Schools (Box 7)
  - Sewage Disposal Plant (Box 7)
  - Smith vs. Peekskill (Box 8)
  - Smith, general (Box 8)
  - Spiritual power (Box 8)
  - State Aid (Box 8)
  - Sustenation Society (Box 8)
  - T (Box 8)
  - Trustees Conference, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Unemployment (Box 8)
  - Uniting Experience, 1939 (Box 8)
  - V (Box 8)
  - Veterans Case (Box 8)
  - W (Box 8)
  - Washington (Box 8)
  - Who's Who In Peekskill (Box 8)
  - World War Tablet (Box 8)
  - Y.M.C.A. (Box 8)
- Legal matters
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - City Hall, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - City Court
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Continental Methodist Church (Box 9)
    - Judge Choutos (Box 9)
  - Deeds, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Drew Seminary (Box 9)
  - Federal Government (Box 9)
  - Field Library, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Friendly Town Association
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Museum (Box 10)
  - Old Cemetery (Box 10)
  - Parks Commission, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - School Board (Box 10)
  - State Government (Box 10)
  - Wills (Box 10)
  - Young Mens Christian Association of Peekskill (Box 10)
- Edwin Markham
  - Clippings (Box 10)
  - Correspondence
    - Letters
      - Others (Box 10)
      - Signed (Box 10)
    - Notes, signed (Box 10)
    - Telegrams (Box 10)
    - Others (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous printing (Box 10)
  - Photos (Box 10)
  - Writings (Box 10)
  - Writings, other, 3 folders (Box 10)
- Methodist Church
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Conferences
    - Denver, 1960; 4 folders (Box 11)
    - General, 1964 (Box 11)
    - New York, 1962; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Correspondence (Box 11)
  - Correspondence (Box 12)
  - Reports
    - Annual, 1944-1963; 15 folders (Box 12)
    - General Conference, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Legal (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous
    - Notes (Box 12)
    - Printed material (Box 12)
    - Printed material, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Typewritten material, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Souvenirs (Box 13)
  - Tape recording (Box 13)
  - Unidentified material (Box 13)
- Parental effects
  - Father (Box 13)
  - Sister (Box 13)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous printed material
  - Books, 1792-1966; 11 volumes (Box 14)
  - Pamphlets and magazines (Box 15)
  - Pamphlets and magazines (Box 16)
- Writings
  - Books, 9 volumes (Box 17)
  - Typescripts
    - A Layman's Sermons (Box 17)
    - Abraham Lincoln, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - American Opinion of European Civilization 1760 to 1776, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - Church and State In Maryland 1760 to 1776 (Box 18)
    - Fireplace Essays (Box 18)
    - Firsts (Box 18)
    - Methodists Tryst With God (Box 18)
    - My Visit to the Holyland (Box 18)
    - Peekskill: A Friendly Town (Box 18)
    - The Drama of America, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - The Drama of Lincoln, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - The Drama of St. Paul (Box 18)
    - The Homestead Club, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - The Treasury (Box 18)
    - Twelve Heroes From Palestine to America, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Bound typescripts
    - American Opinion of European Civilization 1760-1766 (Box 19)
  - Short subjects, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Speeches
    - Radio
    - Regular, 4 folders (Box 19)
    - Religious, 4 folders (Box 19)
    - Religious, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Unidentified fragments, 5 folders (Box 20)
  - Shorthand, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Others, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Memoirs, 2 volumes (Box 20)
- Diaries
  - 1897-1967, 88 volumes (Box 21)
- Bound records
  - Miscellaneous, 3 volumes (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 volumes (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 volumes (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 volumes (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 volumes (Box 26)